Papers of George C. Baker 1903-1958 (bulk 1943-1957)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Papers of George C. Baker 1903-1958 (bulk 1943-1957)
SWF 004
George C. Barker
Correspondence, research materials, published and unpublished manuscripts and articles, slides, photographs, and one audio tape, primarily from 1943 to 1957, of anthropologist George C. Barker. The collection documents Barker's anthropological research into folk drama and ritual, the social functions of language, the Pachuco language of Hispanic youths, and Yaqui Indian culture and customs. A 1964 gift to the Southwest Folklore Archives from George C. Barker, Sr. Deaccessioned from the collection in 1993 were approximately 0.2 feet of duplicates and items of a personal nature. In 1996 two 11 x 14 black-and-white photographs by Alfred A. Cohn were transferred to the L. Marguerite Collier Collection, Southwest Folklore Center Manuscripts Collection SWF 005.
8.25 linear feet.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/ E-Mail: LBRY-askspcoll@email.arizona.edu
Restrictions
Restricted. Researchers are restricted to an edited user cassette copy of Barker’s recorded interview of Pachuco language speakers.
Biographical Note
George C. Barker was born on November 15, 1912, in Omaha, Nebraska. He received his A.B. in history from the University of California, Los Angeles, in 1935 and an M.S. in journalism from Columbia University in 1936. After developing an interest in anthropology, he attended the University of Chicago and received an M.A. (1943) and a Ph.D. (1947) in that field. He was elected a Fellow of the American Anthropological Association in 1947.
Despite recurring poor health and physical handicaps, Barker engaged in a number of research activities. His primary areas of interest were folk drama, folk religion, Native American cultures in the Southwest, the social functions of language, and the Pachuco language of Mexican-American youths. He published various works on these topics.
Barker served as a Research Associate at the Institute of Human Relations, Yale University, in 1942, and at the University of Arizona in 1947-48. In 1950 he became a Research Associate in Anthropology at the University of California, Los Angeles, a position he held until his death in 1958. While in Los Angeles, he worked with the Los Angeles County Probation Department and the Neighborhood Youth Association of West Los Angeles on problems of Mexican-American youth.
For additional biographical information, see Harry T. Getty's biographical introduction in the 1958 reissue of: Barker, George C. Pachuco: An American-Spanish Argot and its Social Functions in Tucson, Arizona. University of Arizona Bulletin XXI:1. Social Science Bulletin, no. 18. (Tucson: University of Arizona Press, 1958) [reprinted 1970].
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series.
Series I: Research Materials, 1903, 1929-1958
Series II: Correspondence, 1931, 1940-1958
Series III: Published and Unpublished Articles, Papers and Reviews, 1936-1958
Series IV: Field and Research Notes, 1940-1958
Series V: Poems and Essays, 1927-1956
Series VI: Visual and Audio Materials, 1940s-1950s
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of George C. Barker’s research notes, correspondence and field notes from his research activities. The research notes consist primarily of articles, offprints, newspaper clippings and secondary literature accumulated by Barker during the course of his study and research in bilingualism and folklore. Many items address issues of bilingualism in the southwestern United States, and its social manifestations.
Barker’s correspondence documents exchanges between him and his colleagues in anthropology and folklore, including Edward P. Dozier and Edward H. Spicer. Also included are correspondence with Frances Gillmor, several letters to and from the Reverend Anthony Soto, one family letter, and personal correspondence with Mexican American families in Tucson. The collection includes some correspondence addressed to Barker’s father, George C. Barker, Sr.
Barker’s works include his publications, and drafts of published and unpublished articles, papers, monographs, and reviews, field and research notes from his doctoral thesis and other projects, and transcripts of interviews. There is a handwritten manuscript of Coloquio de pastores del hijo pródigo, transcribed by ensayador Aristéo Flores, from Chapalá, Mexico. This was edited and translated by Barker and published in Folklore Studies: 2 by the University of California Press in 1953.
Visual and audio materials include 379 original kodachrome slides and 151 copies, about 70 of which are of Yaqui village scenes and Holy Week processions in the Yaqui village at Hermosillo, Mexico. The other slides are of travel scenes in various countries, inconclusively referenced in notes for a presentation and an undated index, both stored with the slides. Photographs and negatives include photos of Yaqui Indian ceremonies, several postcards, and unidentified photos of Mexico, Spain, and various ceremonies. The collection includes reel tapes of Pachuco dialogue, songs, and interviews. An edited reel has been made from the original paper tape reel. Personal names have been edited out of this duplicate reel.
Preservation xerostatic copies of a substantial portion of the materials have been made. Boxes 1-5 of the collection contain working copies of the materials, a small number of uncopied originals, and slides and photographs. Original documents of which working copies have been made are stored in boxes 6-9. The working copies of the audio tapes are housed in the Southwest Folklore Center Manuscript Collection SWF 009, with the call numbers 85.2/C.1 and 85.2/R.1.
Researchers must obtain permission from the coordinator of the University of Arizona Southwest Folklore Center or the University of Arizona manuscripts librarian to use the original documents.
Barker, George C. (George Carpenter), 1912-1958.; Dozier, Edward P..; Spicer, Edward Holland, 1906.; Folk drama, Spanish American.; Christmas plays.; Prodigal son (Parable) -- Drama.; Spanish language -- Dialects -- Arizona -- Tucson.; Spanish language -- Social aspects -- Arizona -- Tucson.; Spanish language -- Slang.; Bilingualism -- Arizona -- Tucson.; Mexican Americans -- Arizona -- Tucson -- Languages.; Gangs -- Arizona -- Tucson.; Tucson (Ariz.) --Social life and customs.; Yaqui Indians -- Mexico -- Hermosillo -- Rites and Ceremonies -- Photographs.; Audio tapes.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Slides (Photographs).; Arizona--Tucson.; Tucson (Ariz.).
Container List
- Research Materials, 1903, 1929-1958; Series I
  Books, pamphlets, articles and papers collected by Barker on a variety of sociological, anthropological and folk topics related to Barker's research. There are also newspaper and magazine clippings, programs, minutes, and papers from various activities. Material is arranged by type of material, and thereunder chronologically when possible.
  - Published works, pamphlets, articles, and brochures, 1929-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1-70)
  - Notes and two papers from a conference, "Work Conference on Research Problems of Bilingualism 1954"; and a paper by Leonard Broom and Eshref Shevky, "Mexicans in the United States: A Problem in Social Differentiation", undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Announcements, fliers, programs, street maps, meeting minutes, and miscellaneous materials, 1936-1957 (Box 1, Folder 72-76)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, 1903, 1936-1958 (Box 1, Folder 77)
- Correspondence, 1931, 1940-1958; Series II
  Correspondence between Barker and his colleagues in anthropology and folklore, and with persons regarding sources of information for research. Also included are a family letter and personal letters from Mexican American contacts in Tucson, Arizona and California. Items are arranged chronologically.
  - Letter from Barker to his grandmother, December 21, 1931; Describes a camping trip taken with his father in the previous week. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 1)
  - Letter from Thomas Sebeok to Barker, February 25, 1943; Answers questions Barker posed to him concerning Sebeok’s bilingualism. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 2)
  - Letter from Ralph Beals, Univ. of California, to Barker, December 7, 1943; Responds to Barker’s query regarding areas in which would be appropriate for him to do his dissertation field work on bilingualism. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 3)
  - Letter from Harry T. Getty, Univ. of Arizona, to Barker, Dec. 27, 1943; Discusses possible communities in which Barker could do his dissertation work. Discusses Tucson’s suitability. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 4)
  - Letter from Abe Halpern, Univ. of Chicago, to Barker, June 2, 1944; Transmits materials on language use habits in Guatemala. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 5)
  - Letter from Frank E. Moore to Barker, June 8, 1944; Discusses Redlands, California as a possible location for Barker’s dissertation research. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 6)
  - Letter from Harry T. Getty, Univ. of Arizona, to Barker, June 13, 1944; Discusses language use in the Tucson, Arizona Mexican and Mexican American community. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 7)
  - Letter from Joe Chalita Hernandez to Barker, undated; Conveys personal news (partly in Spanish). (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 8)
  - Letter from Mrs. Joe Hernandez to Barker, March 22, 1946; Personal news of the family and envelope. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 9)
  - Letter from Barker to Manuel Cajero, April 12, 1946; Asks that Cajero fill out and return a language use survey. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 10)
  - Letter from Barker to Ricardo Manzo, April 24, 1946; Describes the preliminary findings of his language use research. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 11)
  - Letter from Barker to Rebecca Mariscal, Alianza Hispano-Americana, April 24, 1946; Asks that Mariscal complete a questionnaire on language use in her family. Attached is a preliminary summary of his research [for Tucson area speakers?]. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 12)
  - Letter from Maria Huerta to Barker, 21 de Mayo de 1946; Conveys family news. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 13)
  - Letter from Maria [Huerta] to Barker, Sept. 3, 1946; Family news. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 14)
  - Letter from Maria Huerta to Barker, 2 de Octobre de 1946; Family news. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 15)
  - Letter from L.E. Romero and Gila to Barker, Dec. 18, 1946; Personal greeting accompanying a Christmas card. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 16)
  - Letter from Mr. and Mrs. J. Hernandez to Mr. and Mrs. George Barker [Sr.], Dec. 18, 1947; Conveys greetings and personal news. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 17)
  - Letter from Barker to Leland Sonnichsen, May 28, 1948; Barker shows Interest in El Paso Pachuco and requests verification of his own information of the origin of the argot. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 18)
  - Letter from Leland Sonnichsen to Barker, June 7, 1948; Has turned over Barker's letter to Gabriel Cordova, a graduate student and former court interpreter who compiled a list of several thousand words of the argot. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 19)
  - Letter from Barker to Leland Sonnichsen, June 10, 1948; Conveys his thanks for the information. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 20)
  - Letter from Barker to Gabriel Cordova, June 15, 1948; Contains acknowledgment of the information given on origin of Pachuco. Gives Barker's professional background and explains his interest in Tucson Pachuco. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 21)
  - Letter from Ned [i.e. Edward Spicer] to Barker, July 27, 1948; Mentions his slow progress on “People of Pascua” and discusses issues and approaches to the "off-reservation research program" on Arizona Indians that he intends to do in conjunction with Barker. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 22)
  - Letter from Barker to Mr. Donald Biery, July 29, 1948; Asks the Superintendent of the Sherman Institute the questions that Spicer raised in his letter (cf. above letter). (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 23)
  - Letter from Barker to Ned [i.e. Edward Spicer], August 3, 1948; Reply to Spicer’s letter of July 27, 1948 (item 22, above). (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 24)
  - Letter from Barker to Ned [i.e. Edward Spicer], August 14, 1948; Reports on a visit to Sherman Institute where he did some preliminary data collecting for a study of off-reservation Arizona Indians. (cf. folder 1, item 23). (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 25)
  - Letter from Maria to Olive [Barker], December 13, 1948; Contains a description of the feast of the Virgin of Guadalupe at Morelia. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 26)
  - Letter from Aristéo Flores to Barker, 26 de Disiembre [sic] de 1948; Thanks Barker for making him aware of another copy of El hijo pródigo. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 27)
  - Letter from Ned [i.e. Edward Spicer] to Barker, September 20, 1948; Reply to Barker’s letter of August 14, 1948 (item 25, above). Also contains a report on his two new books People of Pascua and Potam, a Yaqui Village in Sonora. (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 28)
  - Letter from Barker to Frances Gillmor, May 20, 1950; Describes how he acquired the religious folk drama El hijo pródigo in 1948 and points out the unusual nature of the text which "combines the story of the prodigal son with that of the pilgrimage of the shepherds to Bethlehem." (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 1)
  - Letter from Barker to Frances Gillmor, June 10, 1950; Thanks Gillmor for bibliographical advice and mentions her research on "dance dramas with a ‘fighting pattern.’” (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 2)
  - Letter from Arthur L. Campa to Barker, June 20, 1950; Gives his opinion on the Los pastores play collected by Barker and calls Barker's attention to the two cycles of plays he published in the University of New Mexico Bulletin. (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 3)
  - Letter from Frances Gillmor to Barker, June 30, 1950; Gives bibliographical information for the Los pastores play and discusses publication possibilities. Also mentions Barker's Pachuco bulletin. (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 4)
  - Letter from Frances Gillmor to Barker, July 15, 1950; Mentions the Pachuco bulletin and publication possibilities for Barker's folk play. Also describes progress on folk plays with "fighting patterns." (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 5)
  - Letter from Barker to Dick [family name not given], November 28, 1950; Excerpt of a conversation that Barker had with an informant in West Los Angeles (in Spanish). (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 6)
  - Letter from Barker to Charles F. Harding III, July 13, 1951; Outlines his intended research on "language usage and acculturation among Mexican Americans in Southern California.” (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 7)
  - Letter from Barker to Mr. Robert E.G. Harris, September 27, 1951; Requests information on "wetbacks" for the "occupational survey of persons of Mexican descent in southern California." (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 8)
  - Letter from Ed [i.e. Edward Dozier?] to Barker, December 28, 1951; Largest part of the letter concerns the annual performance of a morality play witnessed at Christmas time in San Antonio, Texas. Attached are “Notes on the presentation of Los pastores.” (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 9)
  - Letter from Aristéo Flores to George and Olive Barker, 5 de Enero de 1952; Conveys personal news and asks the Barkers if they can offer him employment. (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 10)
  - Letter from Barker to Aristéo Flores, 11 Enero, 1952; Responds to the above letter. Offers an address where Flores can inquire about work opportunities. (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 11)
  - Letter from Aristéo Flores to Barker, 16 Enero, 1952; Discusses the possibility of filming a version of El hijo pródigo. Asks if the Barkers have any contacts in the film industry. Asks if the Barkers can assist him in obtaining U.S. citizenship. (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 12)
  - Letter from Barker to Aristéo Flores, 27 Enero, 1952; Responds to the above letter. Explains that he cannot offer help in obtaining U.S. citizenship. (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 13)
  - Letter from Lyle Saunders to Barker, April 22, 1952; Thanks Barker for a reprint of "Growing up in a Bilingual Community." He thinks that a recognition of language and cultural differences will help provide adequate medical care to the Spanish-speaking people of Denver. (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 14)
  - Letter from Barker to Mr. Afton D. Nance, December 2, 1952; Inquires whether the State Department of Education, California, would be interested in an outline for a home study course in citizenship for Mexican immigrants. (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 15)
  - Letter from Barker to George Mann, December 31, 1952; Referred to Mann by Afton Nance. Barker inquires again what programs there for adult Mexican immigrants In English and citizenship. Suggests the possibility of a home study course. (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 16)
  - Letter from George Mann to Barker, January 6, 1953; Expresses interest in the home study course in English and citizenship for adult Mexican immigrants that Barker suggested. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 1)
  - Letter from Barker to George Mann, January 15, 1953; Short note that he Is assembling material for the home study course. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 2)
  - Letter from David L. Olmstead to Barker, March 25, 1953; Responds to a Barker letter [?] dealing with acculturation and language. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 3)
  - Letter from Robert Redfield to Barker, April 13, 1953; Cautions Barker to study bilingualism without applying it to social mobility, delinquency, and jobs based on the data he is going to elicit. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 4)
  - Letter from Waldemar A. Nielsen to Barker, April 20, 1953; Rejection of Barker’s proposal to the Ford Foundation for a bilingual study. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 5)
  - Letter from Barker to Ed [Dozier], April 22, 1953; Contains comments on the manuscript about the Tewa on First Mesa of the Hopi Reservation. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 6)
  - Letter from Barker to David Olmstead, April 23, 1953; Response to Olmstead’s letter of March 25, 1953. Deals with their different opinions on language and acculturation; Barker holds that bilingualism is possible without acculturation while Olmstead has taken the opposite view. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 7)
  - Letter from Barker to R.R. [i.e. Robert Redfield], April 29, 1953; Reply to Redfield’s letter of April 13, 1953 (folder 3, item 4). It is a thank you note and indicates that Barker intends to revise his proposal for the study of bilingualism rejected by the Ford Foundation. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 8)
  - Letter from Stanley H. Robe to Barker, May 27, 1953; Gives a short summary of Juan Rael’s talk on pastores plays at the meeting of the California folklore society. Attached is a sheet that shows the distribution of pastores plays and different types. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 9)
  - Letter from Matt [i.e. T.M. Pearce] to Barker, June 21, 1953; Thanks Barker for sending him Rael’s map on Los pastores plays (cf. above letter) and discusses the conclusions Rael presented at the meeting. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 10)
  - Letter from Kurt H. Wolf, Institut für Sozialforschung an der Johann-Wolfgang-Goethe-Universität, Frankfurt a. Main, Germany, to Barker, July 15, 1953; Discusses his experiences of bilingualism in Germany, especially between High German and German dialect. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 11)
  - Letter from Dave [i.e. David Weingarden] to Barker, July 16, 1953; List of the angel’s names for the study Barker is doing for the Neighborhood Settlement Association. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 12)
  - Postcard from Porfirio Gonzalez to Barker [George C. Barker, Sr.?], July 27, 1953; Discusses payment received for work performed for Barker. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 13)
  - Letter from Einar Haugen, University of Wisconsin, to Barker, July 28, 1953; Inquires about the nature of Barker’s bibliography on bilingualism, and plans for its publication, if any. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 14)
  - Letter from Barker to Kurt [i.e., Kurt H. Wolf], July 29, 1953; Responds to Wolf’s letter of July 15, 1953 (folder 3, item 11). Discusses varieties of English in the U.S. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 15)
  - Letter from Barker to Joseph B. Casagrande, Stanford, July 31, 1953; Reports on his exchange of letters with Wolf and suggests an inter-university seminar on bilingualism. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 16)
  - Letter from Barker to Prof. Einar Haugen, University of Wisconsin, August 10, 1953; Describes the nature of his bibliography on bilingualism, and points out that it will address the “social functions of bilingualism.” (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 17)
  - Letter from Barker to George M. Foster, September 10, 1953; Acknowledges support given in regard to Barker's pastores play and promises a copy of the recently published play. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 18)
  - Letter from Albert R. Marquez to Barker, September 18, 1953; Attached is: "Descendants of First Settlers Witness Dedication of old Rancho Marker," Palisadian XXVI:21 (September 18, 1953), in Spanish. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 19)
  - Letter from Barker to Aurelio M. Espinosa, September 24, 1953; Acknowledges information given on The Shepherds' Play of the Prodigal Son and promises a copy of the play. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 20)
  - Letter from Barker to T. M. Pearce, September 24, 1953; Acknowledges receipt of the copy of The New Mexican Shepherds' Play and mentions the recent publication of Barker's own pastores play. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 21)
  - Letter from Barker to Professor Arthur L. Campa, September 24, 1953; Announces the shipment of an autographed copy of Barker's pastores play and acknowledges Prof. Campa’s "pioneer work in the field of religious folk drama in the Southwest." (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 22)
  - Letter from Peg [i.e. Margaret Mudgett] to Barker, September 25, 1953; Acknowledges the excellent work Barker did for the Neighborhood Settlement Association. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 23)
  - Letter from Barker to Prof. J. Philipson, U. of San Paulo, Sept. 28, 1953; Thanks Philipson for sending him an offprint. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 24)
  - Letter from Barker to Mr. Albert A. Marquez, September 29, 1953; Invites Marquez to attend a playing of his recorded dedication speech of the Marquez Rancho Marker. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 25)
  - Letter from Barker to T.M. Pearce, October 2, 1953; Comments on a paper by Pearce on Los pastores plays and suggests that there might have been a cycle of these plays rather than a master play of which all "episodes" are a part. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 26)
  - Letter from Aurelio M. Espinosa to Barker, October 6, 1953; Acknowledges the receipt of a Los pastores manuscript. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 27)
  - Letter from George M. Foster to Barker, October 8, 1953; Acknowledges the receipt of Barker's published Los pastores play. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 28)
  - Letter from Barker to Everett C. Hughes, October 31, 1953; Accompanies a manuscript submitted to the American Journal of Sociology. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 29)
  - Letter from Barker to Louis J. King, November 25, 1953; Requests that King and Barker compare notes on the "Angels", the follow up study Barker was doing for the Neighborhood Settlement Association. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 30)
  - Letter from Juan B. Real to Barker, December 17, 1953; Acknowledges the complimentary copy of Barker's Los pastores and mentions that Real did not find pastores plays south of Mexico. (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 31)
  - Letter from A.W. Woolsey to Barker, January 26, 1954; Inquires about Barker's The Shepherds' Play of the Prodigal Son and mentions that the Texas State College for Women has two pastores plays. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 1)
  - Letter from Barker to Editor, Fortnight, February 2, 1954; Congratulates the editor on the unbiased article on teenage gangs in Los Angeles and briefly states his own involvement with the Neighborhood Settlement Association. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 2)